all right
[Music]
a systematic review and meta-analysis on
exercise timing for fat metabolism found
that exercising in a completely fasted
state may work best the Japanese team
that published on the similar work in
this area went as far as to assert if
exercise were a pill to burn body fat it
would be effective only when taken
before breakfast
surveys show few people exercised before
breakfast though before asking people to
make the switch we need to make sure
that these tantalizing 24-hour results
translate into weight loss over the long
term there's a solid theoretical basis
but you don't know until you put it to
the test in a study of experimental
weight gain volunteers were fed up to 4
500 calories a day for six weeks while
vigorously exercising a total of 300
minutes a week either always after an
overnight fast or after a meal a control
group who didn't exercise at all gained
about six and a half pounds compared to
three pounds in the exercise after meal
group the pre-meal exercise group worked
out the same amount but only gained
about half as much one and three
quarters pounds what about weight loss
though
20 young women were randomized into
three hours a week of before or after
meal exercise same diet same amount of
exercise and disappointingly about the
same amount of weight loss the premial
exercise group did lose about an extra
pound of body fat the total weight loss
3.5 pounds versus 2.2 pounds but this
did not reach statistical significance
meaning such a small difference could
very well have been due to chance
a study of six weeks of low volume high
intensity interval training before or
after meals similarly failed to show a
difference
one explanation that's been offered for
this failure is that the increased fat
loss during premal exercise might be
neutralized by the Lesser diet-induced
thermogenesis in other words because it
costs our body fewer calories to process
food of weed after compared to before
physical activity when we exercise after
a meal our body gets mixed signals I
mean exercise is all about mobilizing
energy stores for fuel whereas eating is
more about assimilation and storage and
the metabolic challenge presented by the
ensuing hormonal tug of war might be
responsible for the 15 to 40 percent
greater calorie cost this has led some
to recommend exercising after meals to
facilitate weight loss if you do the
math though our body is so efficient at
digesting that the 15 to 40 increase
might only come out to 3 to 12 calories
such a slight difference would be easily
overwhelmed by the huge disparity in fat
loss as confirmed by the 24-hour fat
balance study showing up to 500 calories
of fat burning difference
I would suggest a more reasonable
explanation might be that the clear body
fat deficit on premial exercise days is
made up for by extra fat storage on
non-exercise days your body likes to
hold on to extra body fat if it can and
so on days you're not driving it down it
may try to even things out both of the
failed weight loss studies had people
exercise only three days a week and so
their bodies said most of the week to
compensate the study I'd like to see is
a pre-meal versus post meal exercise on
all or at least most days of the week to
see if we can continue to drive down fat
stores
for those with diabetes though you'd
want to do the opposite you can imagine
how that siphoning effect muscles have
on excess blood sugar during exercise
might be great for those suffering from
elevated blood sugars and indeed
exercising after a meal can bring down
blood sugars as well as some blood sugar
lowering drugs randomized type 2
diabetics to a 20-minute leisurely
stroll about two miles an hour before
dinner versus after dinner and the after
dinner group blunted their blood sugar
spiked 30 percent same meal same amount
of exercise but a significant effect on
blood sugar control thanks to a little
tactical timing even just a 10 minute
walk after a meal may make a difference
so for those with blood sugar problems
it's better to exercise after meals than
before them
blood sugar from a meal starts appearing
in the bloodstream 15 to 20 minutes
after the first bite and is ramping up
by 30 minutes to Peak at around the one
hour mark before declining to premium
levels within a few hours so for optimal
blood sugar control pre-diabetics and
diabetics should start exercising 30
minutes after the start of a meal and
ideally go for an hour to completely
straddle the blood sugar Peak if you had
to choose a single meal to exercise
after it would be dinner due to the
Circadian rhythm of blood sugar control
that wanes throughout the day ideally
then breakfast would be the largest meal
of the day and you'd exercise after that
or exercise after every meal
foreign